<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://www.greenbrigade.org.in/eventphotos/Haritha_2012_6.jpg</img> <date>28-Nov-12 1:33:38 PM</date> <data> Global Trade Fairs Organizer Messe Frankfurt is partnering for the first time with Electric Lamp &amp; Component Manufacturers’ Association of India (ELCOMA) for the 2012 edition of Light India to be held from 5th to 8th October 2012 at Pragati Maidan, New Delhi, India. This Fair will specially focus on environment protection through new technology developed for bringing in energy efficient lighting, thus saving energy resulting to less burning of fuels required to generate power.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Light India is recognized as India’s largest lighting exhibition in terms of exhibitors and visitor numbers and according to Mr. Shyam Sujan, Secretary General of ELCOMA, the 2012 show will be “an even larger exhibition in terms of exhibitors and visitors scale, never seen in India before.” Main theme of the event will be Energy Conservation and a workshop will educate delegates on new technology and applications introduced in lighting. The three day technical seminar would focus on emerging new technologies and applications such as green light technologies. Some of the world’s leading experts and specialists will deliver Technical Papers on subjects most relevant to India and recommendations made during the seminar will form a white paper which will be submitted to the government for decision making and future policy guidelines for sustainable development.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Commenting on the new partnership with ELCOMA, Mr. Raj Manek, Managing Director, Messe Frankfurt Trade Fairs India Pvt Limited, added “Messe Frankfurt is looking forward to bringing its expertise though Light India and with its international connection, Light India participants will have a unique opportunity to update themselves with the latest energy efficient products, technologies, trends and services from across the globe.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Mr, H S Mamak, Advisor to ELCOMA, added further, “The Indian lighting industry welcomes international competition and has upgraded its quality standards using international technology, joint ventures cooperation, trading and exporting.”&lt;br&gt; </data> </post> </raj>