<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://gogreenindia.co.in/images/upcoming.jpg</img> <date>28-Nov-12 1:34:01 PM</date> <data> » New Exhibition and Conference to boost CSR activity in India&lt;br&gt;» UBM to launch new event promoting CSR in India&lt;br&gt;» NGO India 2012 poised to drive businesses with social values &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;21 February, Mumbai: UBM India will launch NGO India 2012 at Epicenter, Gurgaon during 16 - 18 March 2012. The exhibition and conference aims at fostering alliances and networking between the country’s CSR and NGO communities. As more and more corporates realise the brand value and employee engagement benefits gained by developing a planned CSR strategy, the event will help CEOs, Marketing Heads and other CSR specialists to identify opportunities and share best practices in this area.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The event is supported by prominent institutions such as FICCI, Economic Times, Guidestar India, IBM, India CSR, Outlook Business, Oxfam etc and will host stalls fromclose to 150 NGOs and foundations. They will have the opportunity to profile the work they do in front of an audience of India’s corporate houses. There will also be performances and the opportunity to purchase handicraftsmade by NGO communities. Free to attend workshops for NGOs on best practices in governance and other crucial back office skills will be hosted.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In addition, a high level paid-for conference aimed at corporate CEOs, NGOs and government will run concurrently at the same venue on the first two days of the event. Topics will throw insights on The Role of NGOs in Delivering Inclusive and Sustainable Development; Opportunities and Challenges in Executing Social Initiatives and touch other issues involving governance and wider community engagement.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The exhibition follows similar initiatives launched by UBM in otherregions. “We have seen tremendous benefits to the NGOs that have participated in our events in London and Brazil and we hope to replicate this success in India. It has been an excellent platform for NGOs to highlight their work and for CSR professionals to identify and network with NGOs operating in a large number of fields and geographies” said Sanjeev Khaira, Managing Director of UBMIndia. Entry to the exhibition is free to all and the event is open to the general public on the last day, 18 March.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;About UBM India - UBM India is a subsidiary of UBM plc, which is the second largest independent exhibition organiser in the world. It is the largest trade exhibition organiser in India, responsible for 26 exhibitions in different locations across the country. The company is also involved in the organisation of conference programmes throughout India and in the publications of trade journals and magazines. For further details please visit the UBM India website, www.ubmindia.in. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For details on NGO India 2012, please visit www.india-ngo.org&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rob Sahi, Head of Marketing, Exhibitions, UBM India at rob.sahi@ubm.com or +91 22 6709 2467&lt;br&gt;Hena Ahmad, Sr. Project Manager, UBM India at hena.ahmad@ubm.com or + 91 9999600622 &lt;br&gt; </data> </post> </raj>