<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://cdn.environmental-expert.com/files/9876/events/7477/POWER-GENIndiaandCentralAsia2013-400.jpg</img> <date>28-Nov-12 1:34:26 PM</date> <data> POWER-GEN India &amp; Central Asia is the region`s premier conference and exhibition for the power industry. A landmark event in the Indian power sector, POWER-GEN India &amp; Central Asia 2013 is moving from New Delhi to India’s financial hub of Mumbai, where the event was last held in 2010. The event will now take place from 6-8 May 2013 at Bombay Exhibition Centre, the largest venue of its kind in Mumbai. By moving to Mumbai, this high-level conference and exhibition will significantly expand its coverage from the northern part of India which has been the main focus of the event, to include the western and southern regions of India.&lt;br&gt;Under the theme, Indian Power - Time to Deliver, the event brings together decision makers and influencers as well as technical experts and professionals from leading companies involved in the power generation, transmission and distribution within India and around the world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;With a history of attracting over 9,000 attendees from over 70 countries around the globe, POWER-GEN India &amp; Central Asia along with co-located events Renewable Energy World India and HydroVision India, has developed a world-wide reputation for being the leading industry event to address India’s major power challenges.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Use POWER-GEN India &amp; Central Asia's customized Event Planner through DirectEventConnect to plan your entire experience before you get to Mumbai, India.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How It Works:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;My Event Planner is an exhibition organizer and scheduler that lets you view, compare and bookmark exhibiting companies, products and services that interest you while you search the DirectEventConnect exhibitor directory. Best of all it is FREE!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You can build, refine and add to your planner right from your desktop. After you bookmark exhibitors and products, they are automatically saved as favorites and are highlighted on your printable floor plan for you to follow on site.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Search&lt;br&gt;•	Preview who and what will be at the event&lt;br&gt;•	Stay up-to-date on new products and exhibitors in the community with customized newsletters sent directly to you based on your attendee profile&lt;br&gt;•	Request information and book appointments with exhibitors that interest you&lt;br&gt;Save&lt;br&gt;•	Bookmark products and exhibitors that interest you to save to your favorites&lt;br&gt;•	Recommend exhibitors and products to supervisors and colleagues&lt;br&gt;•	Maximize your time at the event and save money by planning ahead with your Event Planner&lt;br&gt;Connect&lt;br&gt;•	Network with other registered attendees and exhibitors&lt;br&gt;•	Build your event planner that lists your favorite exhibitors on a printable floor plan for you to follow at the event&lt;br&gt;•	Print your customized floor plan based on your favorite exhibitors&lt;br&gt;How To Get Started:&lt;br&gt;1.	Create your DirectEventConnect Attendee Profile at www.globalpowergen-community.com/&lt;br&gt;2.	Search the community for products and exhibitors that interest you and save them to your personalized Event Planner&lt;br&gt;3.	Revisit the community often to see updates and add new exhibitors and products and request meetings&lt;br&gt;4.	Print your customized floormap to follow on site&lt;br&gt; </data> </post> </raj>