<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://www.ecology.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/proteas1-300x199.jpg</img> <date>05-Nov-12 5:42:37 PM</date> <data> &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;In response to climate change, will a postage-sized-domain move uphill–and ultimately out of room?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The following is part three in a series on the National Science Foundation’s Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability (SEES) investment. Visit parts one and two in this series.&lt;br&gt;Climate change is on your porch and in your backyard and living room–anywhere you bedeck with flowering plants. Global warming affects favorite flowers of garden and vase. This is true of plants around the world, including the proteas and the pelargoniums native to South Africa.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Pelargoniums are wild ancestors of common geraniums. Proteas, with their vase-shaped bracts surrounding pencil-thin flowers, look like brightly-colored sea anemones.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;During the Northern Hemisphere’s winter, summer comes to South Africa and proteas and pelargoniums bloom in riotous color. On steep, rocky slopes, their red and pink flowers dot the hillsides.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;“As one of the most diverse plant groups in South Africa, the pelargoniums have a variety well beyond what’s available at even the largest U.S. nursery,” says Carl Schlichting, an ecologist and evolutionary biologist at the University of Connecticut who specializes in these flowering plants.&lt;br&gt;But pelargoniums and proteas such as the king protea, which measures 12 inches across and is the national flower of South Africa, are under fire. Some will become extinct. Some already have.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In a region where average temperatures have significantly warmed over the past 30 years, South Africa’s–if not the world’s–most unusual flowers are besieged.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In response, they’re moving uphill to cooler or wetter spots. When will they run out of room? No one knows for sure. But time is of the essence in learning about this ecosystem, says Schlichting.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Yet to be Discovered&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Despite centuries of discovery, most of the planet’s biodiversity remains unknown. The scale of that unrecognized biodiversity is a vital question, scientists believe, given its rapid and permanent loss around the globe. To respond to the need for more knowledge and a better understanding of Earth’s biodiversity, the National Science Foundation (NSF) recently awarded 25 grants in its Dimensions of Biodiversity campaign&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The effort is part of NSF’s Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability (SEES) initiative. Schlichting and colleagues comprise one of the research teams funded.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;“By establishing networks of interdisciplinary, globally-engaged scientists, Dimensions of Biodiversity will have a lasting effect on biodiversity science,” says John Wingfield, NSF assistant director for Biological Sciences. “It has the potential to transform the way we conduct biological research in this arena.”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Dimensions of Biodiversity campaign is important, believes Wingfield, because assessing the living diversity of Earth is not as straightforward as simply listing species. The campaign is transforming how the role and scope of life on Earth is described and understood, he says.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It promotes novel, integrated approaches to identifying and comprehending the evolutionary and ecological significance of biodiversity in today’s changing environment and in the geologic past.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;“Dimensions of Biodiversity is accelerating the pace of biodiversity research and discovery, and it enables scientists to think at grand scales,” says Joann Roskoski, NSF deputy assistant director for Biological Sciences. ”Collaborative teams have formed to tackle some of the big questions using novel and integrative techniques,” she says. “Taxonomists are talking to geneticists; geneticists to ecologists; and ecologists to taxonomists. This is not business as usual.”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;With the loss of Earth’s biodiversity, biologists have found, links in the web of life that provide ecosystem services are being lost; an understanding of the history and future of the living world is being forfeited; and beneficial discoveries in the domains of food, fiber, fuel, pharmaceuticals and bio-inspired innovation are being eliminated.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;That reality has stimulated the NSF awards, co-funded by NSF’s Directorates for Biological Sciences and Geosciences.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;“Dimensions may accomplish in 10 years what, with a piecemeal approach, would have taken 50 years–a half-century we can no longer wait,” says Roskoski.. </data> </post> </raj>