<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://ecology.com/wp-

content/uploads/2010/07/RES-cover-200.jpg</img> <date>05-Nov-12 6:57:31 PM</date> <data> 

The “Renewable Energy Snapshots” report, published this week by the European Commission’s Joint 

Research Centre (JRC), shows that renewable energy sources accounted for 62% (17GW) of the new 

electricity generation capacity installed in the EU27 in 2009. The share rose from 57% in 2008. For the 

second year running, wind energy accounted for the largest share of the new capacity: 10.2 GW out of the 

27.5 GW built, representing 38% of the total. In absolute terms, renewables produced 19.9% of 

Europe’s electricity consumption last year.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Cautious Optimism
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;In 

2009, and in absolute terms, about 19.9% (608 TWh) of Europe’s total electricity consumption (3042 

TWh) came from renewable energy sources. Hydro power contributed with the largest share (11.6%), 

followed by wind (4.2%), biomass (3.5%), and solar (0.4%).
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;With regards to the 

new capacity constructed that same year (27.5 GW), among the renewable sources, 37.1% was wind 

power, 21% photovoltaics (PV), 2.1% biomass, 1.4% hydro and 0.4% concentrated solar power, 

whereas the rest were gas fired power stations (24%), coal fired power stations (8.7%), oil (2.1%), 

waste incineration (1.6%) and nuclear (1.6%)  (see figure1).
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;As not all installed 

technologies operate continuously 24 hours a day, figure 2 shows the expected yearly energy output 

(TWh) from the new capacity. The new gas-fired electricity plants will deliver yearly 28 TWh, followed by 

wind and PV with 20 TWh and 5.6 TWh, respectively.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;If current growth rates are 

maintained, in 2020 up to 1400 TWh of electricity could be generated from renewable sources, the report 

concludes. This would account for approximately 35-40% of overall electricity consumpicies on electricity 

efficiency, and would contribute significantly to the fulfillment of the 20% target for energy generation from 


highlights that cost reducrated implementation will depend on the production volume and not on time.


&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Summary of 2010 Snapshot Findings
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Wind Energy


&lt;br&gt;With more than 74 GW of total installed capacity in 2009, it has already exceeded the 2010 

white paper target of 40 GW by more than 80%. The European Wind Association’s new target aims for 

230 GW of installed capacity (40 GW offshore) by 2020, capable of providing about 20% of Europe’s 

electricity demand.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Biomass&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br&gt;If 

current growth continues, electricity output from biomass could double from 2008 to 2010 (from 108 

TWh to 200 TWh). However, other energy uses such as heat and transport fuels compete for this 

particular source, which could potentially hinder the development of bioelectricity. Being storable for use 

on demand increases its importance as a source of electricity.
&lt;br&gt;


&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Concentrated Solar Power (CSP)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Installed 

capacity is still relatively small in tion and acceleEU, depending on the success of community pol  Europe: 

0.430 GW in May 2010, about 0.5% of the total, but is steadily increasing. An estimated 30 GW could 

be installed by 2020 if the European Solar Industry Initiative ESII is realised. Most CSP projects currently 

under construction are located in Spain.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Solar 

Photovoltaic&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Since 2003, the total installed capacity has doubled each year. 

In 2009 it reached 16 GW, which represents 2% of the overall capacity. The growth will continue, as for 

2010, installations of up to 10 GW are expected. Solar photovoltaic has also exceeded the capacity 

predictions formulated by in the EU white paper on renewable sources of energy.
&lt;br&gt;


&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Other Sources of Power&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Technologies such as 

geothermal, tidal and wave power are still at the R D stage, so they have not yet been included in the 

Renewable Energy Snapshots. Yet, they are likely to be introduced to the market within the next decade. 

As far as hydro generation is concerned, no major increase is expected, as most of the resources are 

already in use. However, pumped hydro will play an increasingly important role as in a storage capacity 

for the other renewable energy resources.tion in thedy </data> </post> </raj>