<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://www.ecology.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/corals1.jpg</img> <date>05-Nov-12 7:06:24 PM</date> <data> &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Corals that host fewer species of algae are less sensitive to disturbances&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;Symbiodinium, it’s technically called, but more popularly it’s known as zooxanthellae. Either way, these microscopic algae that live within a coral’s tissues hold the key to a tropical reef’s ability to withstand environmental stresses.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The effects on tropical reefs of global warming, ocean acidification, pollution, coastal development and overfishing may all come down to how choosy the corals are about their algae tenants.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reef corals are the sum of an animal and the single-celled algae that live inside its tissues. The animal is called the host and the algae are called endosymbionts. It’s a mutually beneficial arrangement. The corals provide the algae with protection in sunlit, shallow seas. The algae produce large amounts of energy through photosynthesis, which the corals use to survive and to build their skeletons.&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;A Critical Relationship&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;The stability of this symbiotic relationship is critical to corals’ survival. When corals lose their algae, they bleach out and often die.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Researchers at the University of Hawaii and other institutions have found that the more flexible corals are about their algal residents, the more sensitive they are to environmental changes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;“It’s exactly the opposite of what we expected,” says Hollie Putnam of the University of Hawaii and lead author of a paper published this week in the journal Proceedings of the Royal Society B.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;“The finding was surprising; we thought that corals exploited the ability to host a variety of Symbiodinium to adapt to climate change.”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But more is not always better, say Putnam and co-authors Michael Stat of the University of Western Australia and the Australian Institute of Marine Science; Xavier Pochon of the Cawthron Institute in Nelson, New Zealand; and Ruth Gates of the University of Hawaii.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;“The relationship of corals to the algae that live within them is fundamental to their biology,” says David Garrison, program director in the National Science Foundation’s (NSF) Division of Ocean Sciences, which funded the research. “This study gives us an important new understanding of how corals are likely to respond to the stresses of environmental change.”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The research was conducted at NSF’s Moorea Coral Reef Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) site, one of 26 such NSF LTER sites around the globe in ecosystems from deserts to freshwater lakes, and from forests to grasslands. </data> </post> </raj>