<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://www.ecology.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/WMC_Copenhagen_2011-07-02_Lisa-Risager.jpg</img> <date>05-Nov-12 7:08:14 PM</date> <data> &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Courtesy of the European Environment Agency&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;With population growth, urbanisation and economic development, the demand for freshwater in urban areas are increasing throughout Europe. At the same time, climate change and pollution are also affecting the availability of water for city residents. How can Europe’s cities continue providing clean freshwater to their residents?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In July 2011 intense rains left parts of Copenhagen flooded. The urban drainage systems could not handle the amount of water that came down in intensities up to 135 mm in two hours. Copenhagen’s water problems did not end there. Shortly after the floods, large parts of the city were affected for weeks by contaminants in the drinking water in connection with water main repairs. Similar types of water-related problems occur in other cities.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More than three quarters of European citizens live in urban areas and rely on clean water in cities. Approximately one fifth of the total freshwater abstracted in Europe supplies public water systems – water that is directed to households, small businesses, hotels, offices, hospitals, schools and some industries.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ensuring a steady supply of clean water to the public is not a simple task. The water system needs to consider many factors including population and household size, changes in the physical characteristics of land surfaces, consumer behaviour, economic sector demands (such as tourist activities), the water’s chemical composition and the logistics of water storage and transport. It also has to factor in the challenges from climate change that can include unexpected flooding, heat waves and periods of water scarcity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To prevent urban water crises, we need to manage water resources effectively at every stage: from the supply of clean water to its different uses by the consumers. This could involve reducing consumption as well as finding new ways of collecting and using water. Water management should also be better integrated within wider urban management while taking into account characteristics of the local environment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Paying for the Water We Use&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;Advances in technology and new pricing systems alone have already been proven to significantly reduce the amount of water used by households, which is typically 60-80 % of the public water supply across Europe. Technological improvements to domestic appliances such as washing machines and dishwashers, for example, have helped reduce water use without requiring a change in behaviour or an awareness of water issues.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More significant improvements are also possible with changes to the use of water for personal hygiene, which currently accounts for 60% of water use in households. Cistern replacement devices in toilets, for example, provide a cheap and simple way to reduce the water used by one litre per flush. Minor adjustments to shower systems, such as by aerating the water flow, can also result in water savings.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As set out in the EU Water Framework Directive, linking the price of water to the volume of water consumed can provide an incentive for a more sustainable use of water. In England and Wales, people living in metered properties use on average 13 % less water than those in unmetered homes. </data> </post> </raj>