<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://www.ecology.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/bats01.jpg</img> <date>05-Nov-12 7:10:18 PM</date> <data> &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Researchers are identifying the important ecological and economic contributions of bats; gleaning lessons from incredible bat abilities that may advance technology; and helping to battle a new fatal bat epidemic&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The sight of bats hanging upside down in creepy caves or fleeing in fluttery flocks from their subterranean haunts at dusk like “bats out of hell” may spook even the most rational, otherwise unflappable observer.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Nevertheless, on every day (and night) but Halloween, these much maligned creatures of the night should be loved, not feared. Why? Because, contrary to popular belief, bats do not attack people; bats do not tangle in people’s hair; and even vampire bats are not true vampires. (Vampire bats lick blood but do not suck blood.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What’s more, unbeknownst to most people, bats make important contributions to ecology, the economy and even to the search for new technologies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Important Ecological Roles of Bats&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bats, which live on all continents except Antarctica, are essential members of many types of ecosystems, ranging from rain forests to deserts. By fulfilling their ecological roles, bats promote biodiversity and support the health of their ecosystems.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The ecological roles of bats include pollinating and dispersing the seeds of hundreds of species of plants. For example, bats serve as major pollinators of many types of cacti that open their flowers only at night, when bats are active. In addition, bats eat copious quantities of insects and other arthropods. On a typical night, a bat consumes the equivalent of its own body weight in these creatures.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Economic Value of Bats&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As bats fulfill their ecological roles, they provide many economically important services. For example, bats serve as essential pollinators for various types of commercially-valuable crops, including bananas, mangos and guavas. In addition, bats consume many crop-eating insects and thereby reduce farmers’ need for pesticides.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All told, according to a 2011 study published in Science, insect consumption by bats reduces the pesticide bill of the agriculture industry in the United States by roughly $22.9 billion per year on average. Another study, partially funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), calculated the average annual value of Brazilian free-tailed bats as pest control for cotton production in eight counties of south-central Texas at about $741,000.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Inspiration for High-Tech Innovations&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bats offer much to the field of biomimetics, which is the science of modeling cutting-edge technologies based on natural forms. After all, the development of sonar for ships and ultrasound was partly inspired by bat echolocation. Echolocation is the navigation system used by most bats to find and follow their quick-moving insect prey at night, sometimes via daring aerial dogfights and speedy chases–all without crashing into trees, buildings or other obstructions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; </data> </post> </raj>