<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://www.greenerideal.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/2336303208_6a9a5a3ab7_z-600x397.jpg</img> <date>28-Nov-12 12:50:32 PM</date> <data> When people are moving to a new home, the first step is usually its renovating. Repair works do make your place look far more comfortable but they fill your home with many harmful toxins such as plumbum, acetone, phenol and other chemicals that may cause harm to our health. Experts in the fields of building and refurbishment confirm only 25% of the materials used are eco-friendly. The remaining 85% can cause severe damages to our physical condition.&lt;br&gt;Here are a few tips for an eco-friendly renovation:&lt;br&gt;1. Never use materials with untypical features – such as quick dry glues and paints. They consist of a higher level of chemicals compared to traditional ones.&lt;br&gt;2. Make sure that you are using the correct technology for installing windows, ventilation, air conditioning, etc.&lt;br&gt;3. When buying materials always ask sellers for a quality certificate&lt;br&gt;4. Do not get into the new home right after the repair works, it is better to wait at least two or three weeks. During this time the impact of the chemicals will decrease.&lt;br&gt;5. Never buy paints and polish that contain plumbum, phenol or acetone.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Probably the most dangerous side effect of renovating. And in particular, of the materials used for it. It can hardly be removed but it can be easily prevented. The first and most important rule here is to ask for a certificate for the level of radiation in the materials when purchasing them. Be careful when choosing this very essential part of your new home and invest your budget in high quality materials as the harmless consequences of the radiation are headache, easily tired, and there are even worse that we do not want to mention.&lt;br&gt;Pollution&lt;br&gt;The most dangerous pollution is the chemical one. Its sources in your home can be the concrete, the carpet, the insulation, glues, paint. The best solution here is to buy materials that are marked as “eco safe”. But please have in mind this writing does not mean that the materials have no chemicals in them, it only means that their amount is lower compared to ordinary materials. That is why the best solution in this case is to make the renovation as soon as you buy the new property and wait for at least a month before moving into the new home.&lt;br&gt;Choose the right wallpapers and paints&lt;br&gt;There is a great variety of wallpapers and paints on the market. This does not make your task easier. Just on the contrary, it even makes it more difficult because the diversity available makes the choice of the best quality materials a hard task. No matter how strange it may seem to you but the best choice for your walls still remains the old fashion paper wallpapers. And when it comes to choosing the glue to stick them on the wall, there are three possibilities – organic glues, non organic and synthetic. The last mentioned contain many solvents that may cause harm to your health (phenol, acetone, etc.) that is why it is best to choose organic glues for the wallpapers.&lt;br&gt;Remember – even the most eco-friendly materials contain chemicals that may be harmful to your health. That is why the best thing you can do beside the choice of eco-materials is to wait at least for two weeks before getting into your new home. At least two. And if you have small kids, this period should be even longer.&lt;br&gt; </data> </post> </raj>