<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://www.greenerideal.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/306754971_829cf6f4f7_z-450x600.jpg</img> <date>28-Nov-12 12:52:24 PM</date> <data> Embracing an eco-friendly lifestyle starts at home. With your family, you can come up with a strategy to help protect the world for future generations. By starting with a few simple suggestions, you’ll have no trouble adjusting to new habits that can save the environment and your money.&lt;br&gt;Plumbing Upgrades&lt;br&gt;Your bathroom’s plumbing may be hurting the environment by wasting too much water. A quick pipe investigation can help you find leaks and other issues. You can also install water saving toilets to help you cut down significantly on the amount of water you use each month. Be sure to encourage your family to change their behavior in the bathroom to save on water. For example, tell your children to turn off the faucet each time they brush their teeth. Leaving the water on for no reason wastes precious and clean water.&lt;br&gt;New and Modern Appliances in the Kitchen&lt;br&gt;Appliance manufacturers have made significant improvements to eco-friendly appliances. If your kitchen appliances are old and worn, consider switching them out for some new appliances. An eco-friendly dishwasher, for example, uses far less water than older models. You can also buy energy-efficient stoves and refrigerators. After equipping your kitchen with these new appliances, you’ll save money and help the environment.&lt;br&gt;You can also change your habits in the kitchen to help your wallet. For example, try to only run your dishwasher when you have a full load of dirty dishes. During the summer, avoid using your oven if possible. Heating up your home during a hot summer day will make your air conditioner work harder and cost you more money.&lt;br&gt;Hybrid Cars&lt;br&gt;If you drive frequently, you should consider buying a hybrid car to help you minimize the impact of your road trips on the environment. These cars use both electricity and petroleum to move. Electric motors are more efficient than gasoline motors, especially for driving in a city. With a hybrid car, drivers can convert gas-guzzling trips into gas-free errand runs. In addition, the electric motor can accelerate the vehicle in place of the gasoline engine; accelerating uses relatively large amounts of fuel. New technologies, including regenerative braking, allow these vehicles to recharge their batteries while driving.&lt;br&gt;Solar Power&lt;br&gt;Installing solar panels on your roof can help you save on your electricity bill by using nature’s energy to power your home. These systems have gradually become more affordable, making them a great choice for homeowners who want to help the environment. Some local governments even offer rebates if you install a system on your home. For success with your solar panels, you need to get at least five hours a day of sunlight in your area.&lt;br&gt;Following the trend towards an eco-friendly home can help you save money and protect the environment for your children. Your journey to transform your home can start with simple changes in your behavior. If you want to make a more meaningful difference, install solar panels or buy a hybrid car.&lt;br&gt; </data> </post> </raj>