<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?> <raj> <post> <img>http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/7f/Blu_Homes_mkSolaire_front2.jpg/220px-Blu_Homes_mkSolaire_front2.jpg</img> <date>28-Nov-12 12:55:04 PM</date> <data> A life cycle assessment (LCA) can help avoid a narrow outlook on environmental, social and economic concerns by assessing a full range of impacts associated with all cradle-to-grave stages of a process: from extraction of raw materials through materials processing, manufacture, distribution, use, repair and maintenance, and disposal or recycling. Impacts taken into account include (among others) embodied energy, global warming potential, resource use, air pollution, water pollution, and waste.&lt;br&gt;In terms of green building, the last few years have seen a shift away from a prescriptive approach, which assumes that certain prescribed practices are better for the environment, toward the scientific evaluation of actual performance through LCA.&lt;br&gt;Although LCA is widely recognized as the best way to evaluate the environmental impacts of buildings (ISO 14040 provides a recognized LCA methodology), it is not yet a consistent requirement of green building rating systems and codes, despite the fact that embodied energy and other life cycle impacts are critical to the design of environmentally responsible buildings.&lt;br&gt;In North America, LCA is rewarded to some extent in the Green Globes速 rating system, and is part of the new American National Standard based on Green Globes,ANSI/GBI 01-2010: Green Building Protocol for Commercial Buildings. LCA is also included as a pilot credit in the LEED system, though a decision has not been made as to whether it will be incorporated fully into the next major revision. The state of California also included LCA as a voluntary measure in its 2010 draft Green Building Standards Code.&lt;br&gt;Although LCA is often perceived as overly complex and time consuming for regular use by design professionals, research organizations such as BRE in the UK and the Athena Sustainable Materials Institute in North America are working to make it more accessible.&lt;br&gt;In the UK, the BRE Green Guide to Specifications offers ratings for 1,500 building materials based on LCA.&lt;br&gt;In North America, the ATHENA速 EcoCalculator for Assemblies provides LCA results for several hundred common building assembles based on data generated by its more complex parent software, the ATHENA速 Impact Estimator for Buildings. (The EcoCalculator is available free at www.athenasmi.org.) Athena software tools are especially useful early in the design process when material choices have far-reaching implications for overall environmental impact. They allow designers to experiment with different material mixes to achieve the most effective combination.&lt;br&gt;A more product-oriented tool is the BEES速 (Building for Environmental and Economic Sustainability) software, which combines environmental measures with economic indicators to provide a final rating. Particularly useful at the specification and procurement stage of a project, BEES 4.0 includes data on 230 products (including generic and manufacturer brands) such as siding and sheathing.&lt;br&gt; </data> </post> </raj>